<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: firefox | Statistically Significant]]></title>
  <link href="http://andland.github.io/blog/categories/firefox/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://andland.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-03T22:03:42-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://andland.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Landgraf]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Easily Access Academic Journals Off Campus with a Firefox Bookmark]]></title>
    <link href="http://andland.github.io/blog/2013/04/18/easily-access-academic-journals-off/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://andland.github.io/blog/2013/04/18/easily-access-academic-journals-off</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
As a grad student, I do lots of searches for research related to my own. When I am off campus, a lot of the relevant results are not open access. In that case, I have to log onto my school's library website and search for the journal or article there. It is quite a hassle. Luckily, I recently noticed that the website is predictably modified after I log into the library. I go to Ohio State University, and before and after logging in the websites will be <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">http://www.jstor.org/...</span> and <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">http://www.jstor.org.proxy.lib.ohio-state.edu/...</span>, for example. It doesn't matter which journal or website I am looking at. If OSU has access, it will show up with <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">.proxy.lib.ohio-state.edu</span> after the .com/.org/etc. <br /><br />So I was able to save myself a few steps by typing that in instead of going through the library's website. I should also be sure to note that typing this in brings you to an OSU log in screen. Only those with valid access can use this shortcut, but I assume other schools have the same setup.<br /><br />This is still more busy work than I would like, so I searched for ways to automatically do this. <a href="http://lifehacker.com/5731656/how-to-perform-nearly-any-task-from-your-browsers-address-bar">Lifehacker</a> has some address bar shortcuts, but nothing that quite works. I came across a&nbsp; Firefox add-on called <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-us/firefox/addon/url-swap/">URL Swap</a> that seems like it could do the trick. However, when setting it up, I happened to find <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/13212976/automatically-modify-url-in-firefox">this post</a> on Stack Overflow. The second answer has exactly what I am looking for, changing <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">.ExtraPart</span> to <span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">.proxy.lib.ohio-state.edu</span>. <br /><br />I created a bookmark on my bookmarks toolbar with the javascript:<br /><blockquote class="tr_bq"><span style="font-family: &quot;Courier New&quot;,Courier,monospace;">javascript:(function(){ var curloc = window.location.toString(); var newloc = curloc.substring(0, curloc.indexOf("/", 8)) + ".proxy.lib.ohio-state.edu" + curloc.substring(curloc.indexOf("/", 8)); location.href=newloc; })()</span></blockquote><br />and it works perfectly. This trick is so useful I wanted to share this trick to save others some time.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
